Guide to the Student Action With Farmworkers records, 1950-2020, bulk 1992-2016 RL.01128
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Administrative Files, 1992-2020; 1992-ongoing and undated; 50 boxes
  - Resource Files and Articles, 1994-2014
    - Resource files, A-M, 1994-2013; 12 folders 1 box (Box 129)
      Resource files assembled by SAF staff contain chiefly printed matter, but also hand-written notes on: pesticide spraying; alcohol use; migrant camp access and related laws (includes testimonials from SAF staff on encounters in the field with landowners and farmers); Cornell University migrant program; Greensboro Justice Fund; health projects by SAF students; human trafficking; and mental health materials, including a refugee health screening form created by the Gates Foundation. Includes three folders of comprehensive listings of services for NC farmworkers.
    - Resource files, N-W, 1995-2014; 10 folders 1 box (Box 130)
      Resource folders contain chiefly printed materials, correspondence, and notes on: NC Farmworkers' Health Project; NC Farmworker's Project (3 folders); occupational safety; an SAF Witness for Peace in Mexico trip; and other topics and organizations. There is also a draft of a paper on SAF by Sion Dayson of the Social Sciences Research Council.
  - Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1993-2016
    Contains photo albums of various SAF related activities and staff.
    - Scrapbooks (Box 22)
    - Photo albums, 1993-1998 and 1999-2003 (Box 23)
    - Migrant Educational Activities photo album, 1999 (Box 23)
    - Photos of youths by Julee (Box 94)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, 1993-2012 and undated; 2 folders (Box 113)
    - Unidentified color snapshots of youth "by Julee" (former staff), 2000s? (Box 131)
    - ITF scenes in the field (color photographs), 2002, 2016; 8 items (Box 131)
      Includes four panoramic photographs taken in the fields.
    - Taco Bell boycott rally with SAF interns (color photograph), circa 2003 (Box 131)
    - SAF interns playing volleyball at camp near Raleigh, NC (black-and-white reproduction), 2010 (Box 131)
      Part of a calendar by Celia Roberts (from note on folder); also includes image on separate page of a youth group in New York, with former SAF intern, Leanne Tory Murphy.
    - Sowing Seeds for Change scrapbook (printed pages and photographs), 2011 (Box 131)
    - Marchers in the street: FLOC (Farm Labor Organizing Committee) and Black Workers for Justice "Construyendo unidad entre morenos y latinos", 2000s? (Oversize-box 147)
    - Fotos y Recuerdos, FLOC scrapbook, 2000s? (Oversize-box 147)
      Spiral-bound album with heavy paper covers, commemorating FLOC (Farm Labor Organizing Committee) activities, including protests, office and field work, and graduations. Consists of color snapshots, one or many to a page, and artistic felt tip pen full-page color drawings of farmworkers and FLOC logos signed by Ricardo Contrera [?] Jr. The cover illustration is of workers in the fields. Includes printed inspirational quotations, some Biblical. Album measures approximately 11x15 inches.
  - Audiovisual Media, 1986?
    - Wrath of Grapes film reel, 1986?
      Film can is marked with the title, Wrath of Grapes, "return to Joan Preiss," and "Triangle Friends of the United Farmworkers, 2722 McDowell St., Durham, NC."
      Appears to be a professionally-produced copy by Image Transform, Inc. of the 1986 documentary film about farmworkers and the grape industry, featuring footage from Cesar Chavez's famous "Wrath of Grapes" speech and campaign against the use of dangerous pesticides, and hazardous working conditions in California agriculture.
      A two-part online video of the film is available through the University of San Diego's Farmworker Movement Documentation Project.
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Consists of a 9" reel of 16 mm film, completely filled, in a plastic film can.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original media closed to use. A viewing copy must be made for access. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this material.
- SAF Student Projects, 1986-2018; 63 boxes
  Original media such as CDs and video cassettes are closed to use; digital files are available on request. As they require advance preparation for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
  Series houses hundreds of files related to SAF's student-oriented documentary and leadership projects including AIM Farmworker Class, Into the Fields (ITF), and Levante. Some projects were created as part of Duke University Documentary Studies classes. Individual projects typically lasted one academic semester, one summer, or several weeks, and usually were carried out by one or two students.
  Materials in this series are divided into three subseries: student and intern applications, SAF project administrative files, and student documentary projects (the largest subgroup).
  The student and intern project files typically include a cover sheet, proposals, interview plans, essays or other narratives, creative writing, oral interviews, transcripts of interviews, digital and analog photographs, negatives, notebooks, handmade photograph albums, short videos, release forms signed by participants (interviewees), and other project materials. the release forms and other documentation ferquently include data on the migrants: ages, origination, and local addresses.
  Privacy laws govern these and other records. In addition, some projects include instructions banning the use of migrant names by request of the participants.
  Audiovisual/digital media have been removed to a separate series for preservation purposes. These may contain still images, document files, sound and video recordings, and artwork. Many folders contain transcripts or excerpts of interviews and printouts of photographs.
  - Intern files, 2003-2014 and undated
    - ITF rejections, A-Z, and application files, A-G, 2003; 19 folders (Box 132)
    - ITF applications, H-V, 2003; 14 folders (Box 133)
    - Individual intern files, A (Box 40)
    - Individual intern files, A-G (Box 41)
    - Individual intern files, G-H (Box 42)
    - Individual intern files, J-R (Box 43)
    - Individual intern files, R-Z (Box 44)
    - Into the Fields student files, 2007-2013, 14 of 30 (Box 96)
    - Into the Fields student files, 2007-2013, 15-30 of 30 folders (Box 97)
    - Applications, 2012-2013; 11 folders (Box 111)
      Applications for Into the Fields, Sowing Seeds for Change, Students Organizing Schools; includes housing applications
    - Individual intern files, A-Z, 2011-2013; 103 folders (Box 112)
    - ITF applications, A-M, 2014; 22 folders (Box 133)
    - ITF applications, S-V, 2014 (Box 134)
  - Intern Referral Service, 1996-2006
    The SAF Intern Referral Service linked interested students with similar organizations in need of interns, and was also seen as a conduit for establishing SAF campus chapters in the U.S. Contents include applications for internships, program listings and directories used for placement, and other resources.
    Although no longer officially in operation under this name, SAF still maintains up-to-date online listings for opportunities.
    - 1999-2006, 1996-2006; approximately 90 folders (Box 64)
    - Applications and directories, 1996-2002; 2 folders (Box 134)
  - Duke Interns in Conscience and Migrant Summer Project, 1986-1992
    This series contains files relating to one of SAF's earliest founding projects. In the early 1980s, Professor Bruce Payne and other faculty and students at Duke founded the Interns in Conscience project of the Hart Leadership Program.
    - Evaluations (Box 25)
    - Fundraising (Box 25)
    - House course (Box 25)
    - Housing (Box 25)
    - Internships (Box 25)
    - Sponsoring Agencies (Box 25)
    - Migrant Summer (Box 25)
  - Into The Fields: Administrative Files, 1991-2018 and undated
    Access to this material is restricted to researchers who have received prior permission from the donor. Consult Research Services for information on obtaining permission to access this material.
    Into the Fields is an internship program in which interns document issues and individuals in farmworker communities. This subseries includes administrative files related to interns and internship operations. General administrative folders are organized chronologically by year. Files on individuals and organizations are organized alphabetically.
    - Original cover letters written to people on waiting list, 1991-1992 (Box 134)
    - General administrative files, 1993 (Box 26)
    - General administrative files, 1993-1994 (Box 27)
    - General administrative files, 1994 (Box 28)
    - General administrative files, 1994-1997 (Box 29)
    - ITF College Assistance Migrant Program (CAMP) information and letters, 1996-1999 (Box 134)
    - General administrative files, 1997-1999 (Box 30)
    - General administrative files, 1999-2001 (Box 31)
    - General administrative files, 2001-2002 (Box 32)
    - General administrative files, 2002-2003 (Box 33)
    - General administrative files, 2002-2007; 5 folders (Box 134)
      Contains 2002-20003 recruitment folder, 2003 wait list, fliers for ITF program, team programs and presentations (2005-2007), and 2017 placement evaluations.
    - General administrative files, 2003-2004 (Box 34)
    - General administrative files, 2004-2005 (Box 35)
    - General administrative files, 2005-2006 (Box 36)
    - General administrative files, 2007-2008 (Box 37)
    - General administrative files, 2008 (Box 38)
    - General administrative files, 2008-2010 (Box 39)
    - General administrative files, 2010-2011 and undated (Box 40)
    - Into the Fields administrative files, 2010-2011, 1 of 7 (Box 95)
    - Into the Fields administrative files, 2010-2011, 2-7 of 7 (Box 96)
    - Into the Fields and Sowing Seeds for Change programs administrative files, 2011, 9 folders (Box 97)
    - General administrative files, 1995-2009; 17 folders (Box 110)
      Folklife documentary project guidelines and handouts, farmworker stories articles, LAWCHA documentary workshop materials, yearbook, booklet
    - General administrative files, 2010-2013; 32 folders (Box 111)
      Into the Fields: documentary award paperwork
      Joint programs between Into the Fields and Sowing Seeds for change: CAP training, evaluations and reports, orientation, retreats, selection day materials, site visits, sponser applications
    - Notebooks, 2002; undated (Box 113)
      Contains various meeting minutes and notes
    - Food Justice program file, 2011-2013 (Box 134)
    - General administrative files, 2012-2014, 2018; 11 folders (Box 135)
      Organized by date. Includes fellowship resource file, sponsor organizations and training, site visits, an intern file for L. Haynes, professional development and goal charts completed by interns, documentary equipment sign-out sheet, and six folders of theater evaluations.
    - Partner organizations, A-Z (Box 45)
    - Partner universities A-B (Box 45)
    - Partner universities, B-Z (Box 46)
    - Partner organizations, oversized (Box 47)
  - Into the Fields: Student Documentary Work, 1990-2015 and undated
    Contains documentary projects created by SAF's Into the Fields interns and students, arranged by year; some groups are further arranged by student last name. The projects usually consist of paper records as well as audiovisual media, and may contain recorded interviews, interview transcripts, print and digital photos, and student/intern essays, blog posts, reflection notebooks, and occasional artwork. Interview materials are often in Spanish as well as English.
    Projects are centered around living and working conditions and social life in migrant farmworker communities. Many focus on aspects of folklife and the day-to-day lives of individuals. Multi-year ITF projects taken up by groups of students include "Recollections of Home" and "Folklife Documentary Projects." Each individual component project under these project umbrellas is individually foldered with the project title and student name(s).
    Audio, video, and digital media, chiefly containing recorded interviews, videos, and digital photographs, have been separated from the project papers for preservation reasons, and are located in the Audiovisual and Digital Materials subseries within the Student Project series. Additional materials were often posted by the interns and students to online repositories administered by SAF but may not be present in this collection.
    Original media carriers such as optical discs are closed to use; digital files are available on request. As they require advance preparation for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
    - W-9: Life's Learnings: Educations, 1991, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      By: Sarah Carroll.
    - Miscellaneous photos, 1991-2002, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
    - W-2: Oral and Written Comp. number 1, 1991-1994, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      Incomplete document, by: Sarah Carroll and Mike Evans, undated
      A Birthday for Emilia, by: Eric Jones, 1991 Nov. 24
      To all migrant farmworkers everywhere, by: LeeAnn Schrage, 1994
      How Much Do You Earn An Hour?, by: Reyna Nunez, 1994
      El Dia de Nuestra Salud/The Day of Our Health, A summary of the 1994 Hispanic Health Fair, by: Patience Harrison, 1994
      Untitled, by: Tammi Spruill, 1994
      Untitled, by: Veronica Hough, 1994
      Various poems and Some Thoughts on the Summer of 1994, by: Kathy Ray, 1994
      Untitled, by: Naomi Senzer
      From My Experience in Rockingham County, Little Willie, by: Montenique Nikkie L. Finney, 1994 July 27
      Don't Cry, by: Amy Glenn, 1994
      Untitled, by: Kate Graves, 1994
      Untitled, by: Martha Rodriguez, 1994 Aug. 4
      Journal Entry, by: Marla Randall, 1994 Aug. 2
      Little Guatemala, by: Gerardo Martinez, 1994 Aug. 5
      SAF Staff Orientation Rap, no author, 1994
      Creative abstract inspired summer 1994 internship, by: Tobie Bass, 1994
    - Staff scrapbook, 1995, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
    - P-3: Documentary Scrapbook III, 1995, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      Subject photos and staff photos.
    - W-7: Marla Goode's Summer, 1995, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
    - W-8: The Peaceable Classroom, 1995, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      By: Tara P. Knight.
    - W-2: Oral and Written Comp II, 1995-1997, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      Various poems by Alma Rojas, date: 1995
      Journal of an Outreach Worker, by: Palmar Plonk, date: 1995
      Untitled, by: Kiki Barnes, date: 1995
      Untitled, by: Juana Torres, 1995
      Mis Padres, by: Juana Torres, 1995
      Rescuing Gems from Caves and Flowers Deserts, Building Raging Fires from Smoldering Embers, by: Hugh H. Davis, 1995 Aug. 5
      Untitled, by: Cindi Lopez, 1995
      SAF Documentary Project, by: Myah Cook, 1995 Aug. 4
      A ?Better? Life, by: Lori White, 1996
      Untitled, by: Andrea Hickle, 1996 July 28
      Mi escuela es Mt. View, by: Edith Ledezma, 1996 May 16
      A History Lesson, by: Sarah Hennessey, 1996
      Sunflower Seeds, by: Tracy Thorpe, 1996
      Merry Christmas, by: Ramiro Arceo, 1996
      Una Entrevista con Felipe Dejuki Mendoza, no author, 1997
      Surveys administered by Lisa Stevenson, 1997
      The Inside Scoop on the Former Moxley Family Farmers, by: Jenny Sousk, 1997
      Opportunity of a Lifetime, by: Michelle Steiner, 1997
      Las Condiciones de los Trabajadores Agrícolas en Carolina del Norte, by: Hortencia Huerta, 1997
      Untitled, by: Rachel Avery, 1997
      Ese Varado, by: Marcella Hurtado Gomez, 1997 Aug. 5
    - W-11: A Teacher's Summer, 1996, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      By: Ben Edwards.
    - W-1: Field of Dreams...The Real Thing, 1997, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      By: Crystal Denise Hudson.
    - W-4: Maria Luisa Vela and Sharon, 1997, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      Title: Maria Luisa Vela, 19 Years Old, interviewed by: Kris Adams, 1997 July.
    - W-3 Work with Three Students, 1997, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
    - W-6: Feeding the World's Children, 1997, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      By: Luis Mendoza.
    - W-5: Two Interns: Luis and Ethan, 1997, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
      By: Ethan Leander Timm.
    - 1998 Theater Group, 1 of 1 (Box 48)
    - W-12: Living the American Dream, 1998, 1 of 2 (Box 48)
      Untitled photos by Donna Risteen
      The History of una Historia, by: Lynne Walter
      Photos and commentary titled: Celia and Studying Spanish, by: Janeth Serrano
      Economic Justice, by: Tony Macias
      Photograph taken by a farmworker (2), by: Ben Cook
      Settled Out but Not Settled Down, by: Andrea Robinson
      Various photos by Lane Gary
      Brenda Garcia - Tobacco Farmworker, by: Erica Lian
      Untitled photos by Delia Aguirre
      Clarence Ferguson - Telamon Corporation, by: Erica Lian
      Various photos by Candice Stringfield
      Tobacco Field Blues, by: Daniel Hill
      Various photos by Rosa Cruz
      It's a hard life, but a good life; by: Kendra Strauss
      A Classroom, by: Esteban Echeverría
    - W-12: Living the American Dream, 1998, 2 of 2 (Box 48)
      Untitled photo by Donna Risteen
      Documentary Project, by: Cindy Lopez
      Various photos by Alma Rodriguez
      Untitled poem by Michelle Otis
      Untitled photo by Esteban Echeverria
      Domestic Violence, by: Donna Risteen
      Las Hermanas, by: Alicia Doran
      Farmwork Irony at a Camp, by: Janeth Serrano
      Te Gusta Mi Casa?, by: Luis Maciel
      Untitled, by: Andy Smith
      Across the Nation, by: Irma Diaz
      Various photos by Shaundra Young
      Oral History of Sheila Payne, in her home in Durham NC, by: Melinda Steele, 1998 July 31
      FLOC Rally at Mt. Olive Park, speeches by: Virginia Nismith, Fernando Cuevas, James Andrews, Baldemar Velasquez, 1998 June 23
    - A Compilation of Documentary Works, 1999-2000, 1 of 4 (Box 48)
      2000 Into the Fields Interviews
      Interviews with Lorena Ramirez by Danielle Davis, 1999
      Various photos by Wendy Sellers Campbell, 1999
      Aluminum Siding Warrior, by: Brady Rochford, 1999
      With Mom and Dad Quinceañera, by: Luis Velasco, 1999
      La Reina Del Pueblo, by: Laura McFarland, 1999
    - A Compilation of Documentary Works, 1999-2000, 2 of 4 (Box 48)
      Interviews with Lorena Ramirez by Danielle Davis
    - A Compilation of Documentary Works, 1999-2000, 3 of 4 (Box 48)
      Life on Easy Street, by: Rachel LaCour, 1999
      Untitled, by: Kate Rhodes, 1999
      Mango y Fresas, by: Angeline Echeverria, 1999
      Mi Forta/Mi Torta, by: Maria Garcia Campos, 1999
      Various photos by: Jennifer Sugg, 1999
    - A Compilation of Documentary Works, 1999-2000, 4 of 4 (Box 48)
      The Piñata Summer, by: Ellen Szedon, 1999
      Jose Juan's Life History, by: Juan Carlos Vieyra, 1999
      Manuel Deciga's Life History, by: Juan Carlos Vieyra, 1999
      La Criatura Da la Bienvenida, by: Maria Garcia Campos, 1999
    - 1999 SAF interns, loose slides (Box 48)
    - Educ. 300 (class), slides, 1999-2001, 2 folders (Box 48)
    - Subject photo slides, 1999 and 2002; artwork slides, undated (Box 48)
    - Intern photos, Hannah Little and Gina Humble, 1999 and 2003 (Box 48)
    - Southern Folklife box 2, slides, 2000 (Box 48)
    - Subject photo slides, 2000-2002 (Box 48)
    - Juxtaposition, by Angela Callanan, Farmworkers in NC, 2000 April (Box 48)
    - Folklife Documentary slides, 1999-2002 (Box 48)
      Recollections of Home, subseries as follows:
      Section 1: Music and Dance Traditions, by: Alison Blaine, Jesse Gonzales, Ben Campos, Gerardo Martinez
      Section 2: Oral Traditions, by: Laura Greeson, Scott Pryor, Lorena Alvarez, Laxmi Haynes, William Norton
      Section 3: Artisans, by: Dulce Ibarra, Monica Smith, Susan Hicks, Jean Mathurin, Curran Geist, Andrea Waddle, Magdalena Villagran, Nkechi Ukwu, Coby Jansen
      Section 4: Culinary Traditions, by: Shana Jordon, Karla Rosenberg, Juana Ortiz, Alma Navarette, Raul de Anda, Hope Bastian
      Section 5: Religious and Ceremonial Traditions, by: E. Szedon, Brian Eichner, Marivel Gomez, Natasha McDonald, Erin Barker, Maria Ruelas, Bonnie DeBlois
    - CIW [Coalition of Immokalee Workers] Action in Florida, 2000 (Box 48)
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 1 of 7 (Box 48)
      In Their Own Words: Children's Interpretations of Folklife, by: Laura Greeson
      Salvador Tovar, by: Alison Blaine, 2000 Aug. 9
      The Hold Religion Has, by: Lee Abernathy, 2000 July 24
      El Grupo Folklorico del Catedral del Sagrado Corazón, by: Sarah Betson
      Versos, by: Benito Hernandes, 2000 July 25
      Maria Baltazar's Crocheting, by: Monica Smith and Dulce Ibarra, 2000 June 22
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 2 of 7 (Box 48)
      Preface, by: Jim Hemming and Melinda Wiggins
      Interview - Baldemar Velasquez, by: Maria Alapisco
      The Folklorico Dance Group of the Cathedral of the Sacred Heart, by: Sarah Betson
      The Hold Religion Has, by: Lee Abernathy
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 3 of 7 (Box 48)
      El Nuevo Sonido de Appalachia: Mariachi Tradition in the Western North Carolina Mountains, by: Alison Blaine
      I Love My Child, by: Ayesham Coleman
      In Their Own Words - Children's Interpretation of Folklife, by: Laura Greeson.
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 4 of 7 (Box 48)
      The Heart of Tradition, by: Anna Harvin
      Versos - Expressing Your Feelings, by: Benito Hernandez
      Knitting the Threads of Life - The Crocheted Works of Maria Baltazar, by: Monica Smith and Dulce Ibarra
      Food for Thought, by: Shana Jordan
      Retrato de Petra, by: Margarita Martinez; Title: Evolution of Culture through Farmwork
      Nirav Mehta; Title: A Dedication to the Migrant Farmworkers
      Rafhy Levi Bracero Figueroa
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 5 of 7 (Box 48)
      Overcoming the Odds, by: Felipe Olvera
      Love in the Fields of NC, by: Leodoro Perales
      The Artesanía of Nicacio Reyes Reins, by: Jasmine Rocke and Laura Podolsky
      Federico and His Guitar, by: Raquel Rico
      Festival Foods, by: Terry Skorewics
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 6 of 7 (Box 49)
      Title: Faith Meets Tradition - Baptism and Three-year old Presentation in One Migrant Family, by: Ana Viego
    - Recollections of Home, 2000, 7 of 7 (Box 49)
      Food for Thought, by: Shana Jordan, 2000 July 19
      Retrato de Petra, by: Margarita Martinez
      The Artesanía of Nicacio Reyes Reina, by: Laura Podolsky, 2000 July 30
      How Federico learned to play the guitar and some songs from his repertoire, by: Raquel Rico, 2000 July 21
      Festival Foods and Music, by: Terry Skorewicz, 2000 July 30
      Faith Meets Tradition, by: Ana Viego, 2000 August 11
    - Into the Fields, 2001 (Box 49)
      Interns' artwork.
    - 2001 Folklife Documentary Project, 1 of 5 (Box 49)
      Juan Flores' Favorite Pastime, by: Jean G. Mathurin, 2001 July 11
      Artesanía, by: Jean G. Mathuria, 2001 July 9
      Juan Flores' Belt making, by: Susan Hicks, 2001 July 9
      De Niña a Mujer, by: Erin Barker and Maria Ruelas
    - 2001 Folklife Documentary Project, 2 of 5 (Box 49)
      Words that Draw the Distance Near: The Poetry of a Migrant Farmworker and the Tradition of Family, by: Scott Pryor
      Carlos Mora's Hog Killing Tradition, by: Karla Rosenberg
      A Man's Promise to the Virgin Mary, by: Brian Eichner and Marivel Gomez
    - 2001 Folklife Documentary Project, 3 of 5 (Box 49)
      La Comida y La Familia, by: Enedelia Rios and Lundon B. Sims
      3rd Birthday Celebration, by: Sylvia Zapata
      Traditional Mexican Food/Meals, by: Curran Geist
      Youth Mural Project - We the future of two merging cultures, by: Curran Geist
    - 2001 Folklife Documentary Project, 4 of 5 (Box 49)
      Migrant Camp Food, by: Chris Watchson and Michael Sinohai, 2001 August
      La Banda y La Realidad, by: Beth O'Donnel and Hannah Armstrong, 2001 July